Guide to the Isaac Ferris Papers MC 76
New York University Archives
Isaac Ferris Papers
Bulk, 1816-1871
1816-1931
MC 76
New York University Archives
0.4 linear feet
Biography
Isaac Ferris, 1798-1873, was a clergyman in the Reformed Dutch Church of America and a University administrator. He served the Second Church at Albany, N.Y. (1824-1836), and the Market Street Church in New York City (1836-1853) before assuming the chancellorship of New York University (then the University of the City of New York) in 1853, a position he held until 1870. Ferris was also founder of the Rutgers Female Institute in New York (1839), member of the American Bible Society (1840-1873), founder of the New York YMCA (1852), and corresponding secretary for the Board of Foreign Missions of the Reformed Dutch Church.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes manuscripts, letters, memorabilia, and printed material pertaining to Isaac Ferris, the third chancellor of New York University.
Arrangement
The collection consists of a single series, in which items are arranged chronologically.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research without restrictions.
Source of Acquisition
This collection was donated to the University Archives by Mrs. Morris P. Ferris and Mrs. J. Stewart McNally.
- Speeches and Addresses, 1816-1931
  - List of printed sermons and speeches, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Commencement Address at Columbia College, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Address at the Opening of the Rutgers Female Institute, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Christmas Day poem, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Ecclesiastical Characteristics: A Plain Statement of the Characteristics of the Protestant Dutch Church"; Discourse before the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Address delivered on the formation of the YMCA of New York, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Anniversary address delivered at the New York Opthalmic Hospital, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Address delivered at the opening of the Law Department, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "The Duties of the Times": preached on the National Thanksgiving, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Jubilee Memorial of the American Bible Society: 1816-1866, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Semi-Centennial Memorial Discourse of the New York Sunday School Union, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Address delivered at the Centennial Proceedings at the North Dutch Church, 1769-1869 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Alumni notes to Ferris on his retirement, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Memorial Discourse; or, Fifty Years Ministry in the Reformed Church of America", 1871 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Receipt, Alumnae Association, Rutgers Institute, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Lecture outline and notes, invitation to attend anniversary meeting of Philomathean & Eucleian Societies, correspondence, clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence of Mrs. Morris P. Ferris, 1927-1931 (Box 1, Folder 17)